Guide to the Robert Triffin Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Inventory, [1934-1978]; 35; (35 boxes)
  - Papers
    - Impact of the Voluntary Program upon International Financing (NICB paper), 1966 February (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Adjustment Policies (Zurich paper), 1966 January (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - E.E.C. Memo: Trois Problèmes, 1966 August (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Ligue Européene de Coopération Economique (ELEC) (7 folders), 1966 August (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Symington letter, 1966 October (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Triffin's Questions on the Reuff and Bernstein Plans, 1967 January (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Comments on Questionnaire Answers (Group of 32), undated (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Letter to the Editor of The Banker, 1960 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - A Simplified Scheme..., undated (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - A Statistical Framework, undated (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Balance of Payments See-Saw, undated (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - Adjustment Mechanism to Differential Rates of Monetary Expension Among the Countries of the E.E.C., 1962 (Box 12, Folder 15)
    - Unused drafts, undated (Box 12, Folder 16)
    - Gold Pool and Conversion Account, 1967 (Box 12, Folder 17)
    - Final draft tables on historical monetary statistics (for eventual checking), 1800-1962 (Box 12, Folder 18)
    - Nineteenth century monetary estimate, undated (Box 12, Folder 19)
    - International Monetary Problem after Rio, undated (Box 12, Folder 20)
    - Perroux, François, undated (Box 12, Folder 21)
    - U.S. and U.K. - E.E.C. B.P. and Reserve estimates, 19th century, 1963 June (Box 12, Folder 22)
    - Money tables, undated (Box 12, Folder 23)
    - Catalog cards, old library (possibly Social science or Economic growth Center), Undated (Box 12, Folder 24-25)
      - Additional material, Undated (Box 12A, Folder 1-2)
  - Card file, old library of Economic Growth Center, undated (Box 13)
  - University governance
    - Flood, Merrill M., Let's Redesign Democracy, 1976 (Box 13)
    - Yale Student's Movements
      - Wright Hall, 1969 (Box 13)
      - Dining Hall employees, 1970 (Box 13)
    - Lasswell seminar, 1969, undated (Box 13)
    - Undergraduate senate, 1970 (Box 13)
    - Triffin papers on participating democracy, Lasswell colloquium and the future (5 folders), 1970, undated (Box 13)
  - European Payments Union (EPU)
    - Confidential Notes for the Managing Board, Bank for International Settlements (BIS) (13 folders), 1952-1959 (Box 13)
    - Confidential Notes for the Managing Board, BIS (4 folders, 1 folder of duplicates), 1950-1952 (Box 14)
    - Monthly Agents' Reports (12 folders), 1953-1959 (Box 14)
    - Monthly Agents' Reports (5 folders, 1 folder of duplicates), 1950-1952 (Box 15)
    - OEEC Council minutes and speeches (Box 15)
    - OEEC Stassen statements, 1953-1954 (Box 15)
    - OEEC Summary of Plan of Action for 1949-1950, 1949 April (Box 15)
    - OEEC Code for Liberalization (4 folders), 1952 (Box 15)
    - International meeting: Economic Problems of European Federation (12 folders), 1952 (Box 15)
    - Council of Europe, 1949 (Box 15)
    - Ligue Européene de Coopération Economique (ELEC) (7 folders), 1950-1953 (Box 15)
    - European Monetary Committee (2 folders), 1952 (Box 15)
    - Miscellaneous (4 folders), 1948, undated (Box 15)
    - Pre-EPU-IEPA (3 folders), 1947-1949 (Box 15)
    - Pre-EPU-IEPA (4 folders), 1948 October-1949 June (Box 15)
    - Pre-EPU-IEPA (8 folders), 1947 June-1950 June (Box 15)
    - EPU Negotiations - sterling (20 folders), 1950 (Box 15)
    - EPU Negotiations - quotas and credits (8 folders), 1950 (Box 16)
    - EPU Negotiations (32 folders), 1949-1950 (Box 16)
    - OEEC-EPU Revisions (28 folders), 1952-1954 (Box 16)
    - [EPU Revisions: Triffin papers, empty] (Box 16)
    - EPU Revisions, country proposals (41 folders), 1949-1954 (Box 16)
    - EPU Revisions, miscellaneous (14 folders), 1950-1954, undated (Box 16)
    - Convertibility (24 folders), 1952-1955, undated (Box 16)
    - EPU and IMF (9 folders), 1950-1953 (Box 16)
    - EPU Operations, miscellaneous (25 folders), 1951-1953, undated (Box 16)
    - Supplementary statistical tables (3 folders), 1950, undated (Box 16)
    - Aides-Memoires for Central Banks, #1-36 (5 folders, 2 folders of duplicates), 1950-1957 (Box 17)
    - Supplementary statistical tables, series 1-12 (4 folders), 1950-1954 (Box 17)
    - Special statistical tables, 1951-1952 (Box 17)
    - Exchange Control and Quantitative Trade Restrictions, 1946 (Box 17)
    - Unit of Account, 1968, undated (Box 17)
    - Unit of Account, new tables, 1966-1967, undated (Box 17)
    - Euro-Dollar and related paper, 1957-1969, undated (Box 17)
    - Action Committee for United States of Europe, 1961-1967 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - CEE documents, 1962 (Box 18)
    - Free Trade Area and Jean Monnet (6 folders), 1958-1965, undated (Box 18)
    - Unit of Account (Unité de Compte), 1958-1966 (Box 18, Folder 10)
    - Unit of Account, 1963-1965, 1958-1978, undated (Box 18, Folder 11)
    - Unit of Account, prospectus file, 1969-1971 (Box 18, Folder 12)
    - French loan negotiations (3 folders), 1946 (Box 18)
    - Papers on EPU, 1950-1951, undated (Box 18)
    - IMF - Establishment of Par Values, 1945-1953 (Box 18)
    - European Payments Union and Latin American, Triffin (2 copies), 1952 July 21 (Box 19)
    - Triffin Mission to Cuba, 1952 (Box 19)
    - Revision, 1950-1958 (Box 19)
    - Triffin papers for ECA on EPU Negotiations, 1949 October-1950 September (Box 19)
    - Triffin EPU proposals (2 folders), 1947-1949 (Box 19)
  - International Monetary Fund (IMF)
    - European Payment Agreement Board Discussion, 1949 (Box 19)
    - Decisions on Triffin's EPU proposal by IMF staff, 1947 September-1949 December (Box 19)
    - Excerpts from The Genesis of the EPU, McNaughton (2 folders), [1948-1949] (Box 19)
    - Reports as European observer primarily on European payments discussions (2 folders), 1948-1949 (Box 19)
    - Major Triffin papers on IMF policy, 1949 July-September (Box 19)
    - Correspondence and papers (14 folders including duplicates), 1946-1948, undated (Box 19)
    - Consolidated list of all IMF research and material, 1946-1954 (Box 19)
    - Economic Conditions in Western Europe Following World War II, 1945-1956, undated (Box 20)
    - National and International Measures for Full Employment, comment, Hexner and Fisher, 1950 (Box 20)
    - BIS on Marshall Plan, 1947 (Box 20)
    - Anglo-American Agreements, 1945-1945 (Box 20)
    - Multi-lateral Clearing with Multiple rates, 1949 (Box 20)
    - Purchasing Power Parity Computations, Polak, 1948 (Box 20)
    - Monetary Arrangements for Non-Soviet World, Bissell, 1953 (Box 20)
    - Study on Multilateral Clearing for ECLA, Thompson, 1949 (Box 20)
    - The Hague Club, 1956 (Box 20)
    - Convertibility, 1947-1955 (Box 20)
    - Inflation in Western Europe, Horsefield, 1948-1949 (Box 20)
    - Inflation in Latin America, Horsefield, 1949 (Box 20)
    - Unit of Account, 1958-1961, 1957-1960, undated (Box 20)
    - Unit of Account, Collin meeting, 1957-1959, undated (Box 20)
    - Unit of Account, Chase and Lombard calculations, 1972-1974 (Box 20)
  - European Economic Community (EEC or CEE)
    - Other studies and pamphlets, 1956-1960, 1957-1962, 1959-1962 (Box 20)
    - Monetary problems, 1949-1962 (Box 20)
    - Official internal memoranda, 1959-1964, undated (Box 20)
    - Proposal for discussion, 1964-1965, undated (Box 20)
    - United Kingdom, 1961, undated (Box 20)
    - Tariffs (2 folders), 1957-1959, undated (Box 20)
    - Monetary Committee, France, 1961 (Box 21)
    - Studies on Monetary Integration, 1958-1959 (Box 21)
    - Garvey, George, Discount Mechanism in Leading Industrial Countries Since World War II, undated (Box 21)
  - Recent Economic Developments (printed material)
    - Nepal (Asia), 1968 (Box 21)
    - Austria, 1960-1966 (Box 21)
    - Belgium, 1953-1967 (Box 21)
    - Canada, 1963-1967 (Box 21)
    - Chile, 1967 (Box 21)
    - Colombia, 1967 (Box 21)
    - France (6 folders), 1956-1970 (Box 21)
    - France, Major Addresses...of General Charles deGaulle (2 copies), 1964 (Box 21)
    - Germany, 1956-1967 (Box 22)
    - Greece, 1956-1968 (Box 22)
    - Iceland, 1960-1965 (Box 22)
    - Indonesia, [undated] (Box 22)
    - Ireland, 1960-1966 (Box 22)
    - Ireland and Portugal, 1956-1958 (Box 22)
    - Portugal, 1960-1964 (Box 22)
    - Israel, 1969 (Box 22)
    - Italy, 1953-1969 (Box 22)
    - Japan, 1965-1971 (Box 22)
    - Netherlands, 1960-1966 (Box 22)
    - Norway, 1960-1965 (Box 22)
    - Peru, 1969 (Box 23)
    - Singapore, 1969 (Box 23)
    - Spain, 1960-1966 (Box 23)
    - Sweden (2 folders), 1953-1966 (Box 23)
    - Switzerland, 1959-1966 (Box 23)
    - Turkey, 1956-1966 (Box 23)
    - United Kingdom (2 folders), 1953-1966 (Box 23)
    - United States, 1953-1968 (Box 23)
    - U.S. Council of Economic Advisers-Washington, 1969 (Box 23)
    - Yugoslavia, 1962-1966 (Box 23)
    - Other, [1965] (Box 23)
    - Chase Manhattan Bank
      - Annual Foreign Trade Service, 1967 (Box 23)
      - Latin American Business Highlights, 1966 (Box 23)
      - Report on Western Europe, 1966 (Box 23)
    - Comptes Rendus, 1951-1964 (Box 23)
    - Stock Markets and The Economy of Western Europe-Monthly Review, 1964 (Box 23)
  - Files on Monetary Systems and Banking
    - Latin America (by country), 1912-1954, undated
      - Other countries, 1910-1954, undated (Box 24)
      - U.S A. (empty) (Box 24)
    - Monetary Banking (empty) (Box 24)
    - Sterling Area (foldered by country), 1947-1956, undated (Box 24)
    - Europe
      - General Europe, 1946-1953, undated (Box 24)
      - Folders by country, Albania-Austria, 1924-1946 (Box 24)
      - Folders by country, Belgium-Yugoslavia, 1946-1954, undated (Box 25)
    - Printed economic reports, mostly on individual Latin American countries, 1947-1959 (Box 25)
    - International Monetary Fund (black binder), Statistical Report on Czechoslovakia, 1947 November (Box 25)
    - Federal Reserve System, Board of Governors, mimeo reports
      - Austria-Bulgaria, 1944-1945, undated (Box 25)
      - Denmark-Yugoslavia, 1944-1945, undated (Box 26)
    - Federal Reserve Internal Papers (Box 26)
    - Economic reports by individuals on International Monetary Problems
      - Cooper, Richard, 1970-1973 (Box 26)
      - Emminger, Otmar, 1971 (Box 26)
      - Fleisig, H., undated (Box 26)
      - Friedman, Milton, 1971 (Box 26)
      - Woehrling, F., 1975-[1976?] (Box 26)
      - Others, good papers (2 folders), 1972-1977, undated (Box 26)
  - Research material
    - Magnifico Group, 1975 March (Box 27)
    - European Unit of Account, 1975 March (Box 27)
    - Triffin Missions, Belgium, Guatemala (personal) documents, grant forms, etc.), 1971-1972 (Box 27)
    - ESCAFE Mission (Belgium), Informal Expert Consultations on Regional Trade Liberalization and Payments Arrangements, report, 1970 (Box 27)
    - Multinational corporations (Box 27)
    - COMECON (Box 27)
    - Developing countries (Box 27)
    - de Groote (Box 27)
    - FECOM (Box 27)
    - EEC Papers, 1972-1974 (Box 27)
    - Unsorted printed material (Box 27)
    - SDR-World Central Bank (Box 27)
    - Centro Europeo di Studi-Jozzi-Torino, 1977 (Box 27)
    - Euro-Dollar Market (Box 27)
    - Latin America (Box 27)
    - Link Proposal (Box 27)
    - Economics Dept., printed material for classes (Box 27)
    - China (Box 28)
    - ECAFE Missions on Asian Payments Union, 1967
      - Asian Clearing Unit, 1971-1975, undated (Box 28)
      - Asian Reserve Bank, 1972 August (Box 28)
      - ECAFE (3 folders), 1970 (Box 28)
    - Siddique, Abul K.M., The International Monetary and Economic Conferences of the Inter-War Period, dissertation, 1970 (Box 28)
    - Cameron, Duncan Charles, La Système Monétaire International en voie de Reforme les Travaux du Comité des Vingt, dissertation, 1975 (Box 28)
    - East-West Studies, printed material, Circa 1976 (Box 28)
    - International Monetary System and related topics, unsorted articles and papers (Box 29)
    - Printed material including:
      - Bank of Greece papers and lectures, Xenophon (Box 30)
      - Zolofas, 1960-1967 (Box 30)
      - National Economic Policy and the International Monetary System, papers, 1977 (Box 30)
      - Y.U. Economic Growth Center Papers, 1977-1978 (Box 30)
      - Bulletin S.E.D E.I.S. (Société D'Etudes et de Documentation Économiques Industrielles et Sociales) (2 folders), 1959-1960 (Box 30)
      - Analyse and Prévision, SEDEIS, 1966-1967 (Box 30)
  - Unpublished works by Robert Triffin (black binders)
    - Monopolistic Competition and General Equilibrium Theory, volume, 1938 October (Box 31)
    - First draft of thesis on "Monopolistic Competitivity...," typescript, 2 small binders, undated (Box 31)
    - Short pieces, drafts of books (early works)
      - Projet de thése de doctorat, and others, binder, undated (Box 31)
      - Typescripts and mss. unpublished books and articles, binder, 1939-1940 (Box 31)
      - Unidentified mss., binder, undated (Box 31)
      - Histoire des théories économiques, binder, undated (Box 31)
    - Tables, old and unclassified (2 folders), undated (Box 31)
    - International Integration of B.P., Reserve statistics (Econ. 182), undated (Box 31)
  - Books by Robert Triffin, including translation into other languages, 14 items (Box 31)
  - Articles and Speeches
    - Notes, drafts and reprints
      - International Monetary Co-op in Asia and the Far East (2 folders), 1969 (Box 32)
      - International Economic Policy Issues, 1969, 1968 November (Box 32)
      - "International Monetary Crisis: What Went Wrong?", 1968 November (Box 32)
      - Japan and Development of Asia on Prof. Triffin's APU, 1968 November (Box 32)
      - The Oriental Economist, 1968 October (Box 32)
      - National Industrial Conference Board, 1968 September (Box 32)
      - Unsorted articles and speeches (Box 32)
      - World Money Maze, 1947-1953, undated (Box 32)
      - Miscellaneous articles, undated (Box 32)
      - Kant quotation, 1975 (Box 32)
      - Major French articles, 1950-1965, undated (Box 32)
      - Table: Sources and Distribution of International Monetary Resources, 1949-1965 (Box 32)
      - Unsorted tables and articles (Box 32)
      - Contribution of Regional Monetary Integration to Worldwide Monetary Reform, 1967 September (Box 32)
      - "Going It Alone in Monetary Reform", 1967 April (Box 32)
    - Reprints, unsorted, 1956-1966, undated (Box 33)
    - Encyclopedia of the Future, unpublished, undated (Box 34)
    - Reprints and volumes, unsorted, 1971-1977, undated (Box 34)
    - Reprints, including a volume and a draft, 1935-1967, undated (Box 35)
    - Reprints by Triffin and others (3 folders), 1969-1978 (Box 35)
  - Correspondence
    - Haas, Ernst B., 1960 (Box 35)
    - Chronological file (2 folders), 1969-1970 (Box 35)
  - Chronological list of publications (Box 35)
- Additional Material, [1935-1978, undated]; 3; (3 boxes)
  Donor: Robert Triffin
  Received: 12/6/79
  - Reprints, 1935-1962 (Box 36)
  - Reprints, 1963-1966 (Box 37)
  - Reprints, 1967-1978, undated (Box 38)